Shavua Tov שבוע טוב, Shavua Tov, we be in the we have
begun our the fifth and final Perek פרק. Perek. We have one
week left of Beitzah ביצה. Beitzah. Today's Daf דף Daf is Lamed
Vav ל"ו Lamed Vav (36). We pick up on the bottom of
Lamed Hey Amud Bet ל"ה ע"ב Lamed Hey Amud Bet from the
after the two dots. It is seven lines from the bottom, Tnan
תנן. Tnan.
And of course today is Yom HaZikaron יום הזיכרון, Yom HaZikaron, so
our learning should be in the Zechut זכות Zechut and the memory
of all those who have fallen in defense and the creation of
the State of Israel.
Okay, so we pick up with our Mishnah משנה Mishnah which talks
about we had a whole funny introduction about the exact text of
the word Mashilin משילין Mashilin and how many other words might sound
like Mashilin משילין Mashilin and mean more or less the same thing.
But now we get to the basic point, which is the allowance
to lower fruit on the roof that's not Muktzah מוקצה Muktzah that
you designated or it finished drying out and to lower it through
a skylight and also to go ahead and cover up things that
it's going to about to rain on them, even though you're not
doing it for Ochel Nefesh אוכל נפש Ochel Nefesh because you're not
going to eat it today. Nevertheless, you're allowed to do it to
protect them so it shouldn't be a Hefsed הפסד. Hefsed. And the
counterbalancing concern might be that as Rashi רש"י Rashi says of Tircha
טירחא Tircha or always there's also the additional question of Uvda D'chol
עובדא דחול. Uvda D'chol. Let's take a look at what our Gemara
גמרא Gemara says. Tnan תנן. Tnan. Mashilin Perot Derech Arubba B'Yom Tov
משילין פירות דרך ארובה ביום טוב. Mashilin Perot Derech Arubba B'Yom Tov.
You can lower down fruit by the
skylight on Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov from the
roof. Ad Kama עד כמה. Ad Kama. How much? How much are
we allowed to do before it starts to get to be
a problem about you know about too much effort or too much
Uvda D'chol עובדא דחול? Uvda D'chol? Amar Rav Zeira Rav Assi v'amre
lah Amar Rav Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan אמר רב זירא רב אסי
ואמרי לה אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rav Zeira Rav
Assi v'amre lah Amar Rav Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan. K'mot sheshaninu כמות
ששנינו K'mot sheshaninu like we taught in Shabbat שבת. Shabbat. We had
a similar discussion about moving fruit around, although for different reasons, and
we're going to follow those parameters. What do we teach over in
Shabbat שבת? Shabbat? What's the Mishnah משנה? Mishnah? Mafnin Arba V'Chamesha Kuppot
Shel Teven V'Shel Tvuah מפנין ארבע וחמש קופות של תבן ושל תבואה.
Mafnin Arba V'Chamesha Kuppot Shel Teven V'Shel Tvuah. You can clear away
the space of four or five boxes. Apparently there was a standard
understanding of what the size of a box is or baskets better
of straw or of grain Mipnei Orchim מפני אורחים Mipnei Orchim if
there are guests. Meaning so you need some extra place to sit
and somehow, you know, you make extra space by moving a I
don't exactly get the scenario. Let'all go out to the barn, let's
all go out to the storage house and we'll make some space
there. Or somehow, but by the moving it, it opens up space
for you to sit. So that's why you're moving it, not to
protect the fruit. U'Mipnei Bittul Beit HaMidrash ומפני ביטול בית המדרש. U'Mipnei
Bittul Beit HaMidrash. Or because of you're causing the loss of the
study hall. Meaning that people want to have a place to sit
and learn and this is a good place. But what you'd have
to do is you'd have to like move a move out a
lot of grain in order to make the space. So you're allowed
to do it, four or five. Now that seems to be under
Now four five could just mean however much you need. But it
understands that no that actually is setting some type of a limit
to it. So then presumably that same quantity would be true here.
Now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says one minute. There are different issues
that are at stake. It's Shabbat שבת, Shabbat, it's Yom Tov יום
טוב. Yom Tov. Why are you doing it? Are you doing it
for guests and for Beit HaMidrash בית המדרש Beit HaMidrash or are
you doing it so that the fruit doesn't rot? And those might
make differences in either direction. So let's take a look. Dilma דילמא
Dilma but maybe Shani Hatam D'ika Bittul Beit HaMidrash שאני התם דאיכא
ביטול בית המדרש. Shani Hatam D'ika Bittul Beit HaMidrash. There there's a
special allowance to do a lot because you know it's in order
to get people otherwise won't have a place to learn or because
of an issue of guests. Aval Hacha D'leika Bittul Beit HaMidrash אבל
הכא דליכא ביטול בית המדרש Aval Hacha D'leika Bittul Beit HaMidrash here
there are not those concerns Lo, we wouldn't allow as much. Inami
אינמי Inami or you can say the opposite
way. Hatam Hai Taama Arba V'Chamesha Kuppot Shari Mishum Shabbat D'Chamira התם
היי טעמא ארבע וחמש קופות שרי משום שבת דחמירא. Hatam Hai Taama
Arba V'Chamesha Kuppot Shari Mishum Shabbat D'Chamira. Maybe there on Shabbat שבת
Shabbat which is very weighty. V'lo Ati Lezilzulei Bei ולא אתי לזלזולי
בה. V'lo Ati Lezilzulei Bei. If we give you allowance to start
moving a lot of hay around you're not going to forget it's
Shabbat שבת. Shabbat. And it's not going to lead to other leniencies.
So we can allow even up to four and five baskets. Aval
Yom Tov D'Kila Ati Lezilzulei Bei יום טוב דקילא אתי לזלזולי בה.
Aval Yom Tov D'Kila Ati Lezilzulei Bei. But Yom Tov יום טוב
Yom Tov which is lighter and it doesn't just mean lighter and
that like it's not Chayav Misa חייב מיתה Chayav Misa for violation
it also means that in practice you wind up doing a lot
more things food related and cooking and all those types of things.
So you know and we've always had this counterbalancing weight of Uvda
D'chol עובדא דחול Uvda D'chol and Tircha טירחא Tircha because we want
to make sure that with all those leniencies of Yom Tov יום
טוב Yom Tov you're still preserving the feeling and the weight of
Yom Tov יום טוב. Yom Tov. So there where those are heightened
concerns Ati Lezilzulei Bei אתי לזלזולי בה Ati Lezilzulei Bei and you'll
come to be lenient Clal Clal Lo כלל כלל לא. Clal Clal
Lo. We won't allow it at all. Now it doesn't literally mean
we don't allow it at all because the Mishnah משנה Mishnah says
that we do allow it but it means that we don't that
we don't allow to the same degree. Okay? So maybe there's you
could have reasons why we have greater allowance on Shab why we
have greater allowance on Shabbat שבת. Shabbat. There's the issue of guests
and Beit HaMidrash בית המדרש. Beit HaMidrash. It's also Shabbat's שבת's Shabbat
weightier. It allows us to be a little bit more lenient. Okay?
Or in but but and therefore those are reasons that Shabbat שבת
Shabbat should be more lenient. But you could also argue the opposite
way. Inami Le-idisa אינמי לאידיתא, Inami Le-idisa, let's opposite the other way
that Yom Tov יום טוב Yom Tov should be more lenient. Hatam
Hai Taama התם היי טעמא... Hatam Hai Taama... There we limit it
to four or five boxes because although there's issues of guests or
בית מדרש, Bais Medrash, it's not issues of loss of property. אבל
הכא דאיכא הפסד ממון, Aval hacha d'ikka hefsed mamon, here that there's
a concern of loss of property, אפילו טובא נמי, Afilu tuva nami,
maybe the Rabbis will allow even more. So that's interesting. Which is
a better big bigger thing that would sort of, you know, give
you greater latitude, a big a bigger push
to be lenient? Is it the issue of guests and learning, or
is it the issue of הפסד ממון? Hefsed mamon? I should also
mention that הפסד ממון Hefsed mamon in addition to like just, you
know, we're concerned that people shouldn't, you know, that their things shouldn't
go to waste, is also a concern that if you don't give
people a certain amount of latitude about this thing, then they're just
going to do whatever they need to do. And you know, so
that comes up in the גמרא Gemara as well. So it's not
just it's a weighty issue and we want to, you know, it
should allow us to override certain concerns. It's also if we don't
give you some, you know, some avenue of doing it, you might
wind up doing it anyway with even greater violation. Okay, so you
could argue either way. So שבת Shabbos give you more allowance or
less allowance? Not clear. Do you take the idea of four and
five baskets and say it should be the same here? Should it
be less here? Should it be more here? You could argue either
way. Now we're going to go through a whole list of things
that are parameters by שבת Shabbos and we want to know if
the same applies by יום טוב Yom Tov in this analogous case
and make the same type of arguments that there's reasons both to
be more strict by יום טוב Yom Tov and to be more
lenient. התם תנן, Hasam tenan, by שבת Shabbos we taught, אבל לא
את האוצר, Aval lo es ha'otzar, you cannot you can while you
can, you know, make space in your in your barn, whatever, to
for guests or for learning, you cannot do it in the storage
house. Now what does that mean? ואמר שמואל, V'amar Shmuel, Shmuel explains
it the following way. מאי אבל לא את האוצר, Mai aval lo
es ha'otzar, what does that mean, not, you know, not the storage
shed? אבל לא יגמור את האוצר כולו, Aval lo yigmor es ha'otzar
kulo, don't clear out the entire shed. Even if the entire shed
only has, you know, or house only has four five baskets. So
we already have the limit of four to five baskets, but let's
say it doesn't it only has like three baskets' worth or four
baskets' worth. You can't clear the whole thing out. Why not? So
we're going to see. דילמא אתי לאשוויי גומות, Dilma asi l'ashvuyei gumos,
if you cleared up the whole space, now you've got a nice
whole exposed floor. Not just you're clearing out a few bundles of
wheat and you have a little bit of a space we can
all gather together and eat there or like, you know, do a
little bit learn our דף יומי, Daf Yomi, fine, we're not trying
to make the whole space nice. But if you cleared out the
whole floor and then the whole place is open, now let's get
out a broom, let's sweep it, let's get it all to look
nice, and then you're going to come to smooth over
a furrows and indentations, which is a because we're talking about a
dirt floor, which is a problem obviously on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, which
is like a type of a to be בונה Boneh and so
on. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא מאי, Hacha mai, so do
we do we have the same limit here that when you're clearing
out your roof, you cannot empty the whole roof? התם הוא בשבת
דאסיר, Hasam hu b'Shabbos d'assir, there it's forbidden on שבת Shabbos משום
דחמיר, mishum d'chamir,
because it's weighty and therefore we're very concerned, concerned that, you know,
you might come to violate שבת. Shabbos. So here's a reason to
be more strict by שבת. Shabbos. אבל יום טוב דקיל, Aval Yom
Tov d'kal, but יום טוב, Yom Tov, which the violation is not
just experientially it's more kal, the violation is less
weighty, שפיר דמי, Shappir dami, we'll allow you to clear out the
whole space. We won't make as much of a גזירה Gzeira that
you'll come to that you'll come to violate. Obviously, if there was
a high concern, we would make it. But at what degree, what
level of concern do
you make a גזירה? Gzeira? So might be in cases where the
violation is a much weightier issue, we'll make more protections even on
the cases that are far that are very unlikely. All right, so
that's one possibility. או דילמא, O dilma, or do you say התם
דאיכא ביטול בית המדרש אמרת לא, Hasam d'ikka bittul Bais Medrash amarta
lo, the opposite argument. If by שבת, Shabbos, even when by we
there's a concern of, you know, of not having a place to
learn, even so we don't let you clear out the whole space
even though there's that sort of weighty justification, הכא דליכא ביטול בית
המדרש לא כל שכן? Hacha d'lekka bittul Bais Medrash lo kol sheken?
So here where there's not that weighty concern of ביטול בית המדרש,
bittul Bais Medrash, certainly we should not let you clear, you know,
clear out the entire space. We should be concerned that you'll come
to sweep it and so on. Obviously, this is a assume, you
know, it's a little bit funny because by שבת Shabbos you're clearing
out the space and you want to you want to use it
as a space. So also the context is you'll come to sweep
it and make it look nice. Whereas by the roof, you're not
going to sit on the roof. You want to get the fruit
down so that you can, you know, so the fruit doesn't get
destroyed or so so the likelihood that it's the whole context that
you're using the space and coming to sweep it besides which, did
they have dirt roofs? I doubt they had dirt roofs. So I
don't even really understand so much the whole you know, it's they're
other issues other than just weighty versus not weighty, ביטול בית המדרש,
bittul Bais Medrash, just the whole context it's not as relevant there.
Is the ביטול בית המדרש bittul Bais Medrash a separate room or
it's in your house? It's the same place and you're going to
use it so you need to clear out, like a separate...
No, that's what it's saying when you're saying we need to. we
need a space to learn, let's go to that place over there,
that shed or that barn, we can move some barrels, you know,
we can move some bushels of wheat and we'll have a place
to sit and learn.
בית מדרש Beis Medrash as a concept.
It's a concept, it seems to be, correct. Okay.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. There's also that real question,
you know, about, I forget the exact scholarship, but the whole idea
that by, in בבל Bavel as opposed to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
you know, in בבל Bavel they much more had the institution of
a בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, whereas, you know, in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, I think they did a lot of learning outside and you
see sort of the, and you see, you know you see when
you see those whole images of like, of you know, but that,
yes, but like you know, of like Plato and Aristotle, what's it
called when they would have the, those learning circles or whatever. Anyway,
there would be, anyway, it'd be like outdoors types of, you know,
learning and anyway, it would not be the same type of a
physical structure to the same degree of an institution. But I don't
remember the details. So yes, בית מדרש Beis Midrash often here is
more of a concept, you just need a place to sit. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So that's one, so we, A, what's the issue about totally clearing
out the space? Is that the same or is that different? What's
the issue about how much we allow you to move? Let's ask
another question. The structure's going to continue for a while.
Okay, והכא תנן, vehacha tenan, here we taught, משחילין פירות דרך ארובה
ביום טוב, mashchilin peiros derech aruba be-Yom Tov, you can lower them
down the skylight. ואמר רב נחמן, ve'amar Rav Nachman, and רב נחמן
Rav Nachman now clarifies, now we're going to ask the opposite direction,
a criterion that we find by יום טוב Yom Tov do we
apply it to שבת? Shabbos? רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, לא שנו
אלא באותו גג, lo shanu ela be-oso gag, that's only you can
lower it from the roof down through the skylight. אבל מגג לגג
לא, aval migag legag lo, but if you had to take it
from one rooftop to another rooftop and lower it down the other
roof skylight, or maybe just moving it to the other rooftop, that's
too much effort, that's too much טרחא, tircha, too much עובדין דחול,
uvdin dechol, that's a problem, that you can't do. ותניא נמי הכי,
vesanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, אין מטלטלין מגג לגג, ein metaltelin
migag legag, you cannot move the grain from one rooftop to the
next, אפילו כשגגותיהן שוין, afilu kshe-gagoseihen shavin, even if they're like even-leveled.
You don't have to climb up or go down, like there's a
lot of effort, right? Even if it's just straight taking a step
over, you know, the gap between the buildings, that's already considered to
be too much. Again, I would also say עובדין דחול uvdin dechol
more, you know, the moving from one roof to another, but either
too much עובדין דחול uvdin dechol or too much טרחא. tircha. So
that's going to be the limit, that's what we get by יום
טוב. Yom Tov. התם מאי, hasam mai, what would be the story
there? Now, you know, again, let's say it would be not again,
you have to try to imagine what exactly would be the scenario,
you know, but you're taking it out of a barn, but let's
say it's not just taking it immediately outdoors from the barn, you
have to שלעפ schlep it, you know, a bit of a while
to another barn. What would be the story? Okay, so התם מאי,
hasam mai,
one minute, okay, I sort of just lost my place.
So we'll skip the parenthesis. הכא הוא דאסר משום יום טוב דקיל
ואתי לזלזולי ביה, hacha hu de-asar mishum Yom Tov dekail ve-asi le-zalzulei
beih,
here we're going to make extra restrictions because since יום טוב Yom
Tov is more light, again, not just the
transgression is less severe, but also experientially it's not, it doesn't feel
as weighty. So you'll come to treat it, you'll come to treat
it lightly. You'll come to, you know, disregard it. And therefore,
therefore, we're going to make extra restrictions. אבל שבת דחמירא ליה, aval
Shabbos de-chamira leih, but שבת Shabbos which is weightier we don't have
to make as many restrictions, you're obviously going to treat it in
a weighty way. We're not concerned ולא אתי לזלזולי ביה, velo asi
le-zalzulei beih, שפיר דמי, shapir dami, then that'll be okay. We'll let
you even שלעפ schlep the grain a little bit. עוד אימא, od
eima, or do we say no, מה הכא דאיכא הפסד פירות אמרת
לא, mah hacha de-ika hefsed peiros amart lo, here, again, you could
argue that there's a greater reason to be lenient because the fruit
will go to waste and even so you put this limit on,
you don't let it go from roof to roof. התם דליכא הפסד
פירות לא כל שכן, hasam delika hefsed peiros lo kol sheken,
so there where there's not a loss of money, certainly we should
have this type of restriction. Okay, so again, reasons to argue that
this case is stricter, reasons to argue that's stricter. We could be
stricter here because אתי לזלזולי, asi le-zalzulei, you'll come to be, it's
in general lighter so therefore we have to put extra restrictions or
else you'll come to treat it, you know, disparagingly. Number one. It
could also be more weighty here
because there's no ביטול בית המדרש. bitul Beis HaMidrash. שבת Shabbos on
the other hand is a reason to say שבת Shabbos is more
weighty. Number one, because it's weightier, it's more weighty. That comes up,
that came up before if there's a real concern of violation. And
it's also, could be that it's more weighty because it doesn't have
the push of הפסד פירות. hefsed peiros. So maybe that allows יום
טוב Yom Tov to be more lenient. So there's arguments to always
be made both ways. Okay, so now let's try again. הכא תניא
hacha tanya or תניא, tanya, here by יום טוב Yom Tov we
have a ברייתא. braisa. Again, all these different parameters, can we apply
it from one to the other? לא ישלשלם בחבל בחלונות ולא יורידם
דרך סולמות. lo yeshalshelem bechevel be-chalonos velo yoridem derech sulamos.
You cannot, this is only you can throw it basically straight down
the skylight, thank you. But if you have to basically, if there's
a window, let's say the rooftop is surrounded by a wall and
there's a window in the wall and what you'd have to do
is you'd have to get it through the window so you have
to lift it up and then lower it down through the window,
or if you have to bring it down by a ladder, that
you're not allowed to do. All you can do is just throw
it down the rooftop. Too much moving and transporting which, you know,
too many picking it up and moving it and getting it down
and all those things, again either too much טרחא tircha the way
Rashi says or too much עובדא דחול. uvda dechol. So that would
be the limit here, very under very limited circumstances. התם מאי? hatam
mai? What would be the story over there by שבת? Shabbos? Let's
say it wouldn't just be taking the hay out of the barn,
let's say you'd have to lift it up on a wagon maybe
and pull the wagon, there'd be more, you know, more movement and
more effort involved. הכא ביום טוב הוא דאסר דליכא ביטול בית המדרש
אבל שבת איכא ביטול בית המדרש שפיר דמי. hacha beyom tov hu
de-asar deleka bittul beit hamidrash aval shabbos ika bittul beit hamidrash shapir
dami. Maybe יום טוב Yom Tov has more restrictions because there's, you
know, not the, it's not a scenario that you'll, you won't be
able to be sitting and learning, but there where it's, there where
it's preventing you from learning, that gives you more leniencies, so it
would be allowed. Or you could also say here it's stricter because
אתי לזלזולי ביה. ati lezulzulei beh. עוד דאמר, od de-amar, or do
we say הכא איכא הפסד פירות? hacha ika hefsed perot? So now
we get back not to the character of שבת Shabbos and יום
טוב, Yom Tov, but in terms of what is the justification?
Is it that the justification of ביטול בית המדרש bittul beit hamidrash
is greater and we'll give you more leniencies, or maybe the justification
of הפסד פירות hefsed perot is greater? Here there's הפסד פירות, hefsed
perot, אמרת לא, amarta lo, and even so you're not allowed to
do too much of a שלעפינג schlepping and moving. התם דליכא הפסד
פירות לא כל שכן? hatam deleka hefsed perot lo kol she-ken? There
where there isn't, in fact, isn't there all the more so that
it should not be allowed? So תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Okay,
so basically it's funny because it sometimes brings, you know, some of
the factors, sometimes it brings others of the factors, but it does
make an interesting point that we have some parameters here, some parameters
there. Very unclear if you can apply them by analogy because by
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, number one is they're dealing
with different sort of justifications. Now, by the way, those justifications you
could imagine a scenario on שבת Shabbat that you have the issue
of הפסד פירות. hefsed perot. It's not like הפסד פירות hefsed perot
is limited to יום טוב Yom Tov realities. You could imagine a
scenario in יום טוב Yom Tov when you have ביטול בית המדרש,
bittul beit hamidrash, right? Although it's interesting, I do wonder whether ביטול
בית המדרש bittul beit hamidrash is a bigger issue on שבת Shabbos
because since יום טוב Yom Tov has this idea of like, you
know, of אוכל okhel and more this idea of שמחה simcha and
so on, maybe on the, you know, maybe there was less learning.
On the other hand, there was also the whole ירחי כלה yarchei
kalla around יום טוב Yom Tov and הלכות יום טוב. hilkhot Yom
Tov. So you could have, so that's just not, you know, intrinsic
to שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, the particular cases were
cases of different justifications. You could imagine them being reversed. And then
you have the issues which were unique to שבת Shabbos and יום
טוב, Yom Tov, that שבת Shabbos is weightier than יום טוב, Yom
Tov, which could mean that we're going to be stricter by שבת,
Shabbos, could mean we're going to be stricter by יום טוב Yom
Tov because since יום טוב Yom Tov isn't as weighty you'll come
to mistreat it, so we have to make more types of restrictions.
So you could go either way and we have no resolution. Yes?
Is this a type of situation in which a פוסק posek would
be completely justified in giving different פסק psak for, because different communities
be different, in other words you weigh the attitude of the קהילה,
kehila, like in other words they seem to be, they're not taking
יום טוב Yom Tov seriously enough, I'm going to come down on
one side, a different community, a different...
Right, so that is true. You know, sometimes you have things which
are, there are general categories which allow for leniencies, you know, צורך
מצוה tsorech mitzvah on שבת, Shabbos, like a שבות דשבות במקום מצוה,
shvut de-shvut bemakom mitzvah, you can do a double דרבנן, derabbanan, a
דרבנן derabbanan of a דרבנן, derabbanan, or מצטער mitzta'er allows you, you
know, to override דרבננ'ס. derabbanans. What constitutes מצטער, mitzta'er, what constitutes a,
you know, מקום מצוה, makom mitzvah, you know, and these types of
things, they remain basically guidelines and then you have to figure out
how to apply them to a concrete case. Here, you know, the
principle is הפסד פירות hefsed perot gives you a certain latitude, ביטול
בית המדרש bittul beit hamidrash gives certain latitude, but it doesn't remain
abstract, it remains very concrete and the גמרא Gemara wants us to
sort of figure out all of the concrete, you know, specific details.
So when it hasn't, are we back in an area now about
like, okay, use your judgment like we would in general? Or because
this has been concretized this way, it maybe takes on more of
the weight of like a specific דרבנן derabbanan that we have to
know exactly what the parameters are? But you are right, this is
a case where if it were not an issue of what did
the Rabbi say initially in their particular allowance, if it was just
a question of principles, then you would use your judgment, you know,
in a case-by-case type of circumstance. Okay, ומכסין את הפירות, umachasin et
haperot, now you can cover up the fruit if it's raining. And
again, what type of fruit we have to imagine? Like it could
be apples, you know, but that's what's the big deal then? But
more likely something like, you know, wheat or grain, it's going to
rain on it, it'll start rotting. Okay, and that you can also
do. Okay, and again, the counter-concern would be one of טרחא tircha
עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, but we will allow you to cover up
your fruit. Okay, אמר עולא, amar Ulla, says עולא, Ulla, ואפילו אוירא
דלבני, v-afilu avira delibnei,
even if we're talking not about fruit but even if we're talking
about like bricks. It's a little funny why the word אוירא, avira,
the הערוך Aruch here says ארא. ara. Anyway, I'm not exactly sure,
but anyway Rashi says we're talking about basically bricks that are stacked
for construction purposes, so they're מוקצה. muktzeh. But if it rains on
them they're going to get either ruined or certainly wet and then
you'll have to wait to dry them out, so it'll be a
whole big טרחא tircha and an effort, you know, and a wasted
time. Okay, so you're even allowed to cover those up. The חידוש
Chiddush being even though they're מוקצה. Muktzah. Obviously there's the same הפסד
Hefsed or more of a הפסד, Hefsed, but even though they're מוקצה.
Muktzah. רבי יצחק אומר: Rabbi Yitzchak Omer: No, פירות הראויים. Peiros Haru'uyin.
You can only cover up fruit which is fit, meaning only cover
up something that itself is not מוקצה. Muktzah. You cannot do an
effort and move something in an effort for something that is מוקצה
Muktzah that it itself could not be moved. You can only move
something for fruit that could be moved. Yes.
But I thought these fruit are meant to dry, in which case
sometimes they are מוקצה. Muktzah.
No, we're assuming that as I said that these are things that
are done drying out and so on and they're not מוקצה. Muktzah.
At least on your roof
and they're on your roof, yeah, they're basically done, you haven't brought
them all indoors or maybe before שבת Shabbos you said I plan
on eating from some of these or something but at least according
to the way רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak because presumably and that's another
point, we're allowing you to do טרחה, Tircha, nobody said we're allowing
you to move מוקצה. Muktzah. Now that's interesting because you'll remember תוספות
Tosafos says אוכל נפש Ochel Nefesh could in some cases override מוקצה
Muktzah concerns. But the assumption of the גמרא Gemara is is that
you're not moving מוקצה Muktzah here. Okay, so it definitely assumes that
the case in the משנה Mishnah where you're lowering the fruit down
the roof is not מוקצה, Muktzah, that they're done drying out or
some scenario like that. Okay and the question is the second degree,
can I move something for the sake of מוקצה? Muktzah? I won't
move the מוקצה Muktzah but I'm moving something for its sake. And
רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says no. So the גמרא Gemara says ואזדא
רבי יצחק לטעמיה, Ve'azda Rabbi Yitzchak Letaimei, רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak goes
according to his general reasoning, דאמר רבי יצחק אין כלי ניטל אלא
לדבר הניטל בשבת. De'amar Rabbi Yitzchak Ein Kli Nital Ela Ledavar Hanital
BeShabbos.
A vessel can only be moved for the sake of something else
that is allowed to be moved. Okay but if you can't move
the object, you can't move something else for the sake of the
object. Alright, תנן, Tnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. Now we're
going to try to figure this out. Does our משנה Mishnah allow
you even if the thing itself is מוקצה? Muktzah? מכסין את הפירות
בכלים, Mechassin Es HaPeiros B'Keilim,
you can cover the fruit with vessels or like with tarp. פירות
אין אררייא דלבני לא? Peiros In Arraiya Delivni Lo?
So look, there's a let's try to infer something. The משנה Mishnah
gave an example of things that aren't מוקצה, Muktzah, gave an example
of פירות. Peiros. The implication being for מוקצה Muktzah objects you wouldn't
have this allowance. He says no, הוא הדין אפילו אררייא
דלבני, Hu Hadin Afilu Arraiya Delivni, you can even move it to
cover up bricks, put a tarp on bricks. ואיידי דתנא רישא משילין
פירות, Ve'aydi DeTana Reisha Mashilin Peiros, תנא סיפא נמי מכסין את הפירות.
Tana Seifa Nami Mechassin Es HaPeiros. Because the first case was lowering
it down from your roof which the scenario of having stuff on
your roof is fruit, so when we talked about covering stuff from
the rain, we're talking about fruit, but לאו דוקא, Lav Davka, you
could cover anything from the
rain. מה תנן? Mah Tnan? Okay, so let's take a look. The
משנה Mishnah continues: וכן כדי יין וכדי שמן, Vechein Kadi Yayin VeKadi
Shemen, you can also cover barrels of you know pitchers of wine
and oil. So why does it keep on giving examples of פירות?
Peiros? Right, give some other example. So הכא
במאי עסקינן? Hacha Bemai Iskinan? So you see that we're underscoring only
food or only things that aren't מוקצה? Muktzah? No. הכא במאי עסקינן
בטבל. Hacha Bemai Iskinan BeTevel.
No, we're talking about wine and oil that is טבל Tevel that
hasn't had תרומות ומעשרות Terumos UMa'asros taken from it, it's מוקצה. Muktzah.
תוספות Tosafos points out even though we said yesterday that בדיעבד B'diavad
if you took תרומות ומעשרות Terumos UMa'asros it would stop being מוקצה,
Muktzah, but for the time being it's מוקצה Muktzah and you can't
move it. That's the scenario. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know
what? הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachinam Mistabra, that makes sense that the second
example was one of טבל. Tevel. דאי סלקא דעתך כדי יין וכדי
שמן דהתירא, De'isalka daitach Kadi Yayin VeKadi Shemen DeHatira,
because if we're talking about just totally, you know, potable wine and
oil, הא תנא ליה רישא Ha Tana Lei Reisha פירות, Peiros, so
we already have an example, פירות, Peiros, so you know we already
said in the beginning fruit, why would it have to give another
example of wine and oil unless it was coming to say even
if it's wine and oil that can't be
eaten that can't be eaten? It says no, כדי יין וכדי שמן
אצטריכא ליה. Kadi Yayin VeKadi Shemen Itztaricha Lei. No no no, it
needed to give that as a second example.
סלקא דעתך אמינא להפסד מרובה חששינן, Salka Daitach Amina LeHefsed Merubeh Chashshinan,
for great loss they were concerned, you know if it rains on
your wheat it'll start rotting and it'll all go back. להפסד מועט,
LeHefsed Mu'at,
for a small loss, that your oil gets a little water in
it or your wine gets a little water in it, לא חששינן,
Lo Chashshinan, that's not as big of a deal. Again, I don't
know, if it gets too watered down who's going to want the
wine, but maybe there's a maybe there's a cover on the barrel,
so maybe or you know so maybe not too much water will
even get through. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that you're even that you're
allowed. So again, while I would have said that actually the משנה
Mishnah does sound that it's underscoring only food, it gives two examples
and they're both food, seems to say we're only talking about food,
the גמרא Gemara sort of goes a little bit the opposite and
says no, since the other example is redundant, it's coming to be
מחדש Mechadesh something else. Maybe it's coming to be מחדש טבל, Mechadesh
Tevel, even stuff that is מוקצה. Muktzah. And then the גמרא Gemara
responds and saying no, it's coming to tell you only food but
even if it's only a להפסד מועט. LeHefsed Mu'at. I can't, I
don't know,
I don't understand, who's going to leave barrels of wine and oil
uncovered anyway and ומגולים UMagulim forget even without that.
So that might be, that might be why it's להפסד מועט, LeHefsed
Mu'at, but still if you have a barrel out in the yard
and it's a heavy rain, the water's going to seep through, you
still want to cover it with a tarp. Alright. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: תנן. Tnan. So we haven't figured it out.
Are you allowed to move things? And this is by the way
more than moving. רבי יצחק's Rabbi Yitzchak principle אין כלי ניטל אלא
לדבר הניטל Ein Kli Nital Ela Ledavar Hanital is even if it's
a trivial effort, it's basically an extension of מוקצה. Muktzah. The same
way this object is מוקצה Muktzah and can't be moved, I can't
move something for the sake of something that can't be moved. Our
משנה Mishnah is dealing with even greater allowance, even a certain amount
of טרחה Tircha being allowed. Okay and that's what we. still haven't
resolved, would our משנה mishna allow you to do it even for
something מוקצה muktzah and in general can you move something for something
מוקצה? muktzah? תנן, Tnan, so let's take a look at another
משנה mishna in שבת. Shabbat. נותנים כלי תחת הדלף בשבת. Nosnim klee
tachat hadelef b'Shabbat.
You can put a vessel, you can put like a pot, underneath
a drip in the roof on שבת. Shabbat. So a drip in
the roof is probably dirty water. That drip is מוקצה. muktzah. That
water is מוקצה muktzah and you're moving a pot for the sake
of something מוקצה. muktzah. Now that's actually interesting, 'cause you could say
no, I'm moving the pot to protect the floor, I'm not trying
to protect the dirty water. It's very different if I'm trying to
protect, you know, the bricks. So it's all about the bricks. Here
it's about saving the floor. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara understands it
it's the same, you're moving it in the for the sake of
to catch something מוקצה, muktzah, so why isn't that a problem? So
the גמרא Gemara says, בדלף הראוי. bedelef harauy. No,
it's a drip that's fit to be eaten. It's like a clean
water that's dripping off of your roof. All right. תא שמע, Ta
shma, come in here. פורסין מחצלת על גבי לבנים בשבת. Porsin machatzel
al gabei l'veinim b'Shabbat.
So you have a ברייתא braita in שבת Shabbat that says you
can spread a tarp,
like a mat, on bricks on שבת. Shabbat. So it's exactly the
case that we said earlier and it says you're allowed to do
it, okay, not a problem even though the bricks are מוקצה. muktzah.
גמרא Gemara says, no, דייתמי מבניינא, d'yitmi mibinyana,
we're talking there about leftover bricks from a construction, they're not still
going to be used for a construction, and דחזי למזגליה d'chazi l'mizgalaya
that they're fit for sitting on. So basically it's bricks, but it's
no longer מוקצה muktzah bricks, they're done using them for construction, it's
leftover and therefore these are you know, they're considered to be something
that you would take and use and make a pile and sit
down on, so it's not
מוקצה.
muktzah. Meaning, the leftover bricks regardless of whether or not you use
them for construction, but if you still could sit on them, but
they're designated for construction you still couldn't do it?
If they're still in use for construction, then they're מוקצה, muktzah, they're
set aside for construction. Yeah, but once they're like leftover and it's
like and then it's understood?
Yeah, right.
The context of being the leftover material from a construction all of
a sudden means that people are going to use it to sit
on.
You could sit on them ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov and
say, you know what, I know they're leftover, I'm gonna use them
on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. You could. Okay. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, תא שמע. Ta shma. פורסין מחצלת על גבי אבנים בשבת. Porsin
machatzel al gabei avanim b'Shabbat. You can protect rocks on שבת. Shabbat.
So rocks מוקצה? muktzah? So says no, באבנים מקורזלות דחזין לבית הכסא.
b'avanim mkurzalot d'chazyun l'beit hakisei. We're talking about like type of sharp
rock, well not too sharp probably, but anyway, appropriately smoothed rocks that
can be used for toilet paper, so they're not מוקצה. muktzah. תא
שמע, Ta shma, come in here. פורסין מחצלת על גבי כוורת דבורים
בשבת. Porsin machatzel al gabei kiveret devorim b'Shabbat. Now the funny thing
is that it's the opposite argument from before. You can get out
of all of these and make them special cases that aren't מוקצה,
muktzah, but the fact that it's applying it to this wide range
of cases, most of which prima facie are מוקצה, muktzah, seems to
be telling me you can do it for מוקצה muktzah objects. But
the גמרא's Gemara going to still try to get out of it.
You can spread a tarp over a beehive on שבת Shabbat in
order to protect it from
rain, בחמה מפני החמה ובגשמים מפני הגשמים, bachama mipnei hachama uvageshamim mipnei
hageshamim, and from the rain for the rain. This is a beehive
that you have to make honey. Okay. ובלבד שלא יתכוין לצודה, uvildad
shelo yitkaven latzuda, as long as you're not trying to trap the
bees. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ah, you see, a beehive
is clearly מוקצה. muktzah. התם נמי דאיכא דבש. Hatam nami d'ika devash.
No, there's honey in the beehive and therefore you're moving it to
protect the honey and the honey isn't מוקצה. muktzah. Again, honey isn't
מוקצה? muktzah? Presumably you could stick your hand in and take the
honey out, although again on שבת Shabbat you're not allowed to take
honey out of the beehive, it would be like תולש, tolesh, probably
can't do it on יום טוב Yom Tov either for the same
reason. So it's funny that it wouldn't be considered מוקצה muktzah even
though you will eat the honey, it's not exactly accessible to you.
Anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. So אמר ליה מר עוקבא ממישן
לרב אשי, amar lei Mar Ukva miMeishan l'Rav Ashi, so Mar Ukva
from Meishan said to Rav Ashi, התינח בימות החמה, hateneich biyemot hachama,
so that makes sense in the summer, דאיכא דבש, d'ika devash, there's
honey in the beehive. בימות הגשמים מאי איכא למימר? Biyemot hageshamim mai
ikka l'meimar? It also says to protect it from the rain. Well
in the rainy season, which is the winter, there's no honey in
there. What are you going to say?
גמרא Gemara says, לא נצרכה אלא לאותן שתי חלות. lo nitzrecha ela
l'otan shetei chalot. No, no, but at least even in the winter
there are two loaves, combs of honey that they leave to feed
themselves in the winter and therefore that's the honey you're protecting. גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, אותן שתי
חלות מוקצות הן. otan shetei chalot muktzot hen. Those two loaves, those
two pieces of honey, combs of honey, are set aside, are מוקצה.
muktzah. You don't want to take it out because then your bees
will die. You're trying to have a business here, you obviously have
to let them have that honey over the winter. גמרא Gemara says
no, הכא במאי עסקינן שחישב עליהם. hacha b'mai askeinan shechishev aleihem. There
you go, Michael. It would be a special case, you thought before
שבת, Shabbat, if I need to, I'll take honey from the beehive
even though it's the winter and even though the bees will die.
Okay, and you made them not מוקצה. muktzah. Again, it's not exactly
clear for me 'cause there's a whole discussion in שבת Shabbat about
how רודה חלות דבש, rodeh chalot devash, how you're allowed to take
honey out of the beehive, but okay. Anyway, it's a case that
they're not מוקצה. muktzah. So גמרא Gemara says, ואי לא חישב עליהם
מאי אסור ve'ilo chishev aleihem mai? Asur? So what would you say
though if he had not designated them? It would be forbidden? Because
they... Says the גמרא, Gemara, אבל לא חישב להם מאי. aval lo
chishev lahem mai. So what would you say though if you had
not designated them? אסור, assur, be forbidden because they would be מוקצה.
muktzeh. עד דתניא ובלבד שלא יתכוין לצוד, ad detanya u-vilvad shelo yiskaven
litzod,
since it says in the end oh but just it's all okay
but just don't plan when you're spreading the tarp to trap the
bees. לפרוש וליתני בדידי. lifrosh ve-lisni bedidi.
Why not have a simpler example of a case being forbidden? Not
when you're trapping the bees, but that when it's not a special
case? במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when are you allowed to
spread the tarp? דחישב עליהן, dechishav aleihen, when you plan to eat
the honey and it's not מוקצה. muktzeh. אבל לא חישב עליהן אסור,
aval lo chishav aleihen assur, but if not that then the hive
is מוקצה muktzeh and you can't move the tarp. So why didn't
it give that? הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar, no here's what the point
of that of it was saying: אף על פי שחישב עליהן, af
al pi she-chishav aleihen,
even in a scenario where it's not מוקצה, muktzeh, there will still
be a case that you can't do it. Of course if it
was מוקצה muktzeh you couldn't do it. And if you didn't set
aside the honey you couldn't do it. But even when it wasn't
מוקצה, muktzeh, there would be a case you couldn't do it. ובלבד
שלא יתכוין לצוד, u-vilvad shelo yiskaven litzod, as long
because you couldn't do it if you were trying to trap the
bees. Okay, so obviously if it were מוקצה muktzeh you couldn't do
it, but you couldn't even do it that. So where are we?
On the one hand our משנה mishna mentioned only food examples which
seems to indicate that it can only be moved to protect non-מוקצה.
muktzeh. On the other example case, all these cases in שבת Shabbat
mention many cases which clearly seem on the face of it to
be מוקצה. muktzeh. The bee hive, the bricks, the stones, etc. and
clearly seem to be you can move it, you can move and
you can, you know, spread a tarp to protect מוקצה, muktzeh, but
the גמרא Gemara has some way of getting out of it and
all of those are special cases that they're not מוקצה. muktzeh. One
minute. So now the גמרא Gemara just takes a little bit of
a break from this מוקצה muktzeh discussion to discuss this last line
of not trying to trap the bees. So גמרא Gemara says like
this. במה אוקימתא? Bamei okimta? רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. דאית ליה מוקצה.
de-is lei muktzeh. Now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. By the
way, there was another way of getting out of all of this
counter evidence that you can spread a tarp to protect מוקצה. muktzeh.
You could have said that all these ברייתות beraitot are going like
רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. And רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon doesn't hold of
מוקצה muktzeh in general or he holds of many fewer cases. And
even if maybe some of these cases he would agree that the
objects are מוקצה, muktzeh, maybe he would be much more lenient about
moving things to protect מוקצה. muktzeh. So you had a much better
answer to get out of all these cases. You could have said
it was all רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. But you didn't, which means
you're assuming that all of these משניות mishnayot are רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda who holds of מוקצה muktzeh and therefore you had to give
a קנייטש kneitch and say it was a special case where it
wasn't מוקצה. muktzeh. But you're assuming that they hold of the principle
that there is מוקצה muktzeh and that you can't move for the
sake of מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, if that's true that it's all רבי
יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, let's look at this issue about trapping. אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, let's look at the end of it. ובלבד שלא יתכוין
לצוד. u-vilvad shelo yiskaven litzod. You cannot intend to trap. אתו כרבי
שמעון דאמר דבר שאינו מתכוין מותר. atu ke-Rebbi Shimon de-amar davar she-eino
miskaven mutar. Why is not intending enough? If you're trapping it, you're
trapping it. What do I care if you intend or not? So
that last line of the משנה mishna has got to be or
the ברייתא beraita has got to be רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Okay,
that says that if you don't intend you're safe. So in any
way says the גמרא Gemara you got an easier answer to all
this stuff, all this is רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, one minute. ותסברא דרבי שמעון היא? ve-tisbera de-Rebbi
Shimon hi? Do you think just saying it's רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
solves the problem in this bee that about not intending? That doesn't
solve the problem. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarvaihu, אביי
Abaye and רבא Rava both say מודי רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא
ימות, modeh Rebbi Shimon be-psik reisha ve-lo yamut, that even רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon who says it's okay if you don't intend would say
when it's a definite consequence it's forbidden. So if you're going to
spread a tarp that's going to totally trap the bees, who cares
whether you're intending or not? You're trapping the bees. So it doesn't
matter whether it's רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda or רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon.
This
ברייתא beraita doesn't make sense. If you're trapping the bees you're trapping
the bees, כוונה kavana shouldn't matter even according to רבי שמעון. Rebbi
Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara says all right. So now let's we
need another way to explain the end of this ברייתא. beraita. לעולם
כולה רבי יהודה היא. le-olam kullah Rebbi Yehuda hi. Fine, it's רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda like we're assuming and there's generally מוקצה muktzeh issues
and there are these crazy special cases. But if it's רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda what's this issue of
trapping? דהכא במאי עסקינן דאית ביה כווי. de-hacha be-mai askinan de-is bei
kavei. There are little windows, meaning even after you cover it there'll
be little ways in which the bees can escape. So therefore it
is not going to be a real case of צידה. tzeida. So
what does it mean don't intend? So it means one minute. ולא
תימא לרבי יהודה ובלבד שלא יתכוין לצוד. ve-lo teima le-Rebbi Yehuda u-vilvad
shelo yiskaven litzod. Don't say, don't have intention to trap because it's
not about intention because anyway A intention doesn't matter and B you're
not because it's רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and D you're not trapping
anyway. אלא אימא ובלבד שלא יעשנה מצודה. ella eima u-vilvad shelo ya'asenah
metzudah. It means don't cover it up fully so that they are
trapped. Okay, it's not about intend. It means don't act in a
way that will trap them. Make sure when you cover it that
you leave them an escape route that you will not trap them.
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, peshita, obvious you can't fully trap them. That's,
you know, certainly it's, you know, we just say כוונה kavana doesn't
matter and if you trap them you trap them. No. מהו דתימא
במינו ניצוד אסור שלא במינו ניצוד מותר. mahu de-teima be-mino nitzod assur
shelo be-mino nitzod mutar. Bees are not normally things that you trap.
Now that's funny because you would say you do trap bees don't
you in order to make a bee hive in order to make
honey, but maybe you attract bees, I really don't know how how
you go around collecting your bees for your bee hive. But it's
considered to be שלא במינו ניצוד. shelo be-mino nitzod. Things that are
normally trapped are things like deer, you know, that you're going to
trap them in order to eat them and and to שחט shecht
them and so on. So therefore it says look, this whole thing
of bees and trapping bees is only דרבנן derabbanan anyway. So therefore
maybe what I would say is that, you know what, since the
whole thing is only rabbinic, if you, maybe it wouldn't be so
bad, you're basically not doing it to trap them, you're doing it
to protect them, so you are an אינו מתכוין, aino miskavein, it
is not really what you're trying to do. And even though it's
it's necessarily going to happen, it's only דרבנן d'rabbanan so maybe we
would allow it, a type of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa on a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So the גמרא Gemara says,
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that no, that even though it's only דרבנן,
d'rabbanan, you cannot do it in a way that definitely traps them.
Now by the way, if again, would it make a difference if
this was רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? In the end of the day,
it's definitely going to happen. Should it, is it really based on
the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon issue or is
it really just saying whatever your position is about אינו מתכוין, aino
miskavein, you cannot do it in a way that totally traps them?
It would seem it should be the same. But תוספות Tosafot says
that the גמרא Gemara still seems to be focusing on רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda a little bit, and he makes an interesting question. He
says, what's considered that you trap them? Let's say, you know, there's
a tiny little hole and if they find the hole and they
squeeze their way out and they sort of, you know, maybe they
can get out. But it's like very unlikely. Are they considered trapped
or not trapped? And he said, you know what, maybe it makes
a difference between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says I don't care about your כוונה
kavana says, you know, okay, you know, it's like who cares, they're
basically trapped. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says, look, if it's not
a פסיק רישא psik reisha you're okay, would say that even if
they're basically trapped, it's not a פסיק רישא psik reisha that they
won't get out, they might find a way to get out and
therefore maybe that will get you off. So תוספות Tosafot wants to
say maybe there still in the end would be a difference about
how to define being trapped. But basically the גמרא's Gemara answer is,
it's not an issue of intent, what do I care about intent
if it actually happens? It says don't do it in a way
that will lead to them being trapped. Okay, רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, מכדי תני בימות החמה ובימות
הגשמים? michdi tani biyemos hachama uviyemos hageshamim? He's going back to an
earlier question. Not how to deal with the end about not having
intent, how to deal with this question about how you can have
honey in it that's not מוקצה muktzah if it's the winter because
it's the rainy season which means the winter. So he says, you
got it wrong. It didn't say in the summer or in the
winter. It says בחמה מפני החמה ובגשמים מפני הגשמים. bachama mipnei hachama
uvageshamim mipnei hageshamim. It says cover it because of the sun or
because of the rain. You never heard of it raining in the
summer? So it says
תני בימי ניסן ובימי תשרי. tani bimei Nissan uvimei Tishrei. We could
be talking about spring or about the fall, דאיכא חמה ואיכא גשמים,
de'ika chama ve'ika geshamim, that a, it sometimes is too sunny, sometimes
it rains, ואיכא דבש, ve'ika devash, and there's honey at those periods.
So we didn't say winter and summer, we said rain and sun.
So therefore there could always be a case of there being honey.
So again, that doesn't address this whole issue about who cares about
כוונה, kavana, that's a problem anyway, כוונה kavana won't matter if you're
trapping, you're trapping. It has to mean you do it in a
way not to trap, but what we are saying is that we
don't have to be talking about the case of מוקצה, muktzah, it
could be that there's honey in the beehive, again I don't know
why because you're not supposed to take the honey out of the
hive on שבת, Shabbat, but anyway there's honey in the hive and
maybe they've already been removed, I don't know exactly the scenario, anyway
it's not מוקצה. muktzah. So bottom line, are you allowed to move
something for the sake of something that cannot be moved? Our משנה
Mishna underscores food, which might seem to say the message of no,
you can only move something for the sake of something not מוקצה
muktzah can you do this, whereas you have a whole string of
Tannaitic material, משנה Mishna and ברייתא Braita in שבת, Shabbat, that seem
to give many scenarios that are מוקצה, muktzah, stones and bricks and
the beehive. And the גמרא Gemara finds a way out of it,
but certainly the simple sense of those is that you can move
it even for the sake of something that is מוקצה. muktzah. Joe,
you had a question?
Yes, I'm just, you know, I'm happy about the whole discussion. I
mean it's really an issue of
מחזי כציידה. mechezi k'tzeida. In other words, the bees live in that
hive, you're really not trapping them in almost, almost no matter what
you do.
I have a question, if I go ahead and I lock your
door and I seal your windows and don't let you out of
your house, could I say well, you live in your house, I
haven't really trapped you?
Okay, we'll think about it. The גמרא Gemara does not say it's
not ציידה tzeida for your reason. It says it's not במינו ניצוד.
bimino nitzod. Right. Okay, all right. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, ונותנין כלי תחת הדלף בשבת. venosnin kli tachat hadelef beShabbat.
And you can also put this pot to catch, you know, under
the drip on שבת. Shabbat. So we already discussed whether the drip
was מוקצה muktzah or not, is it potable or not? And that's
the question of moving something for the sake that can or cannot
be moved. Okay, תנא, tana, we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, אם
נתמלא הכלי
שופך ושונה. im nismaleh hakli shofech veshoneh. If the vessel gets filled
with water, you know, what happens when you got drips? You got
every now and then empty the pot. So fine, empty the pot
and do it again, ואינו נמנע, ve'eino nimna, and you don't have
to and you don't have to withhold yourself. Now why might it
be a problem? A, it might be an effort problem, again עובדא
דחול, ovda d'chol, you're always running and emptying, or we could be
talking again that the water is not potable, so then you're actually
moving מוקצה. muktzah. Now that's going to be interesting, are you allowed
to move מוקצה? muktzah? And that the answer is going to be
in some cases, not for הפסד, hefsed, but for the reason we're
about to find in a minute, and that's what the next case
is about, why this case might be even if the water is
מוקצה. muktzah. So בבי חייא דאביי, bevei Chiyya deAbaye, אביי's Abaye mill.
בי חייא דאביי, bei chaiye de abaye, אביי's abaye grind mill, what
what,
בי
חייא דאביי bei chaiye de abaye דלף dolf was like dripping, okay,
there was so there was it was raining in his mill and
he was afraid that it was going to ruin the millstones. So
אתא לקמיה דרבא, ata lekamei derava, came to רבא, rava, said what
can I do? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, זיל
עייליה לפורייך להתם, zil ayeilei lepurayich lehasam, go bring your bed in
there, turn that into your bedroom, you know, your the room where
your mill is,
דלהוי כגרף של רעי deleihavei k'geraf shel re'i and then the rain
dripping on the millstone will make the millstone like a גרף של
רעי geraf shel re'i is basically a what's it called like a
chamber pot and you'll be allowed to move it, meaning it's making
it smelly, it's not pleasant to be around it, but now you
don't have a good excuse to move it right now because you're
not around it, it's in a different room, it's not in the
room you live in. So fine, go ahead and move your bed
into that room and then it'll be intolerable to have that millstone
together with your bed and then you'll have an excuse to move
the millstone even though it's basically is מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, so the
גמרא gemara says, וכי יתיב אביי וקא קשיא ליה, vechi yasiv abaye
veka kashya lei, so אביי abaye didn't act on this היתר. heter.
He was bothered. He said וכי עושין גרף של רעי לכתחילה? vechi
osin geraf shel re'i lechatchila? This idea that you're allowed to move
a you know a chamber pot even though obviously it's disgusting and
it's מוקצה muktzah both it and the stuff in it, but the
special allowance that they gave you so you don't have to be
around all this smelly stuff, you can't construct the case, you can't
intentionally go and try to make it so the thing is smelly
so you'll have a chance an opportunity to use it. So he
didn't want to rely on this. To him it was too big
of a trick. Okay, אדהכי, adeihachi, so while he was sitting and
not acting on the advice, נפל בי חייא דאביי, nafal bei chaiye
de abaye, so his whole thing collapsed, his house collapsed, the mill.
Okay, אמר, amar, so אביי abaye said, תיפח ליה, teifach lei, you
know, I deserve this דעברי אדמר de'avri admar because I went against
I went against the advice, I was being too frum for myself.
Okay, now now the answer here is that you're not exactly so
תוספות tosafot says, okay, but what about it? Isn't he right that
you're not allowed to do a you know to do a גרף
של רעי לכתחילה? geraf shel re'i lechatchila? So he says look, the
situation was already there, it was already smelling the thing up and
rainy and dripping or whatever, so I wasn't making it a גרף
של רעי, geraf shel re'i, I was just putting myself in its
context. So that is gives me a little bit more of a
lattice. That makes it not so bad because I didn't like make
the thing into that, I just put myself in you know in
front of it. Okay, אמר שמואל, amar shmuel, so presumably by the
way that's the reason you can empty the pot of the rain
water even if the rain water is מוקצה muktzah non-potable because it's
like stinky water or you know sitting around and it becomes a
type of a גרף של רעי. geraf shel re'i. This becomes like
important questions about taking out the garbage, very often our garbage has
in it also things that aren't מוקצה, muktzah, I mean we throw
out so much you know stuff you know that really is edible,
but you know but there are cases in a hospital that other
times of that you have to really remove a baby, how about
a baby diaper, right? You're changing a baby diaper, why can I
go ahead and take it out? Why isn't it מוקצה? muktzah? You
know? So this is a principle of גרף של רעי geraf shel
re'i is an important allowance within the the rules of מוקצה. muktzah.
מאוס ma'us מאוס, ma'us, right. אמר שמואל, amar shmuel, the question is
how bad does it have to be? But you see by the
case of אביי abaye we don't have to be talking literally about
urine and excrement. So אמר שמואל גרף של רעי ועביט של מי
רגלים, amar shmuel geraf shel re'i ve'avit shel mei raglayim, a you
know a pot which is used for excrement or a pot which
is used for urine, so whether it's talking about excrement or urine,
מותר להוציאן לאשפה, mutar lehotzian le'ashpah, you can take them out, that's
what we said, this is this allowance of גרף של רעי, geraf
shel re'i, וכשהוא מחזירו, vecheshehu machziro, now how about when you take
it back? Because then what allows you to bring the chamber pot
back? But the chamber pot even without its contents is disgusting and
is מוקצה. muktzah. So after you've emptied its contents, what lets you
bring it back? So it says נותן בו מים ומחזירו. nosein bo
mayim umachziro. So put water in it so then you sort of
you're allowed to carry it because you're carrying the water. Of course
I don't know if the water is מוקצה muktzah once it gets
into there, okay, but anyway that makes it a little bit more
acceptable to be carrying it back. So סברו מינה, savru minah, so
we assumed גרף של רעי אגב מנא אין בפני עצמו לא, geraf
shel re'i agav mana in bifnei atzmo lo, that they only let
you carry out a chamber pot if you're not directly handling the
excrement, but to directly carry the the disgusting thing out, that much
of an allowance they wouldn't give you. Okay, you could think about
about about you know about people that you know the dog people
that you that do the cleaning up after the dogs, right? And
the the pooper scooper and whatever, although maybe that's also גרף של
רעי, geraf shel re'i, you're not directly handling it. Okay, but maybe
to directly handle it, that would be it would be disgusting, but
also maybe too much of a direct violation of מוקצה. muktzah. תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear that you are even allowed to
directly handle. דההוא אכברתא, de'hahu achbarta, there was a certain weasel or
rat דאשתכח באפרמיקי דרב אשי, de'ishtachach be'afarmikei de'rav ashi, that was in
like the perfume room room of of of רב אשי, rav ashi,
maybe he sold perfume, you do not want dead rats lying around
in your perfume room. So אמר להו רב אשי, amar lehu rav
ashi, so רב אשי rav ashi said, and it was שבת shabbos
or יום טוב, yom tov, נקטוה בדנבתיה ואפקוה, naktuha bedanveteih ve'afkuha, take
it by its tail and and get it out. So there you're
directly handling it. It's not excrement, but it's similar, it doesn't have
to be excrement. We saw אביי. abaye. millhouse and this case of
a rat or other things which are in that category and you
can even handle them directly if you need to.
But it is a little bit funny by the way to think
of the we have just had שבת, Shabbos, it was very beautiful,
we had the שלושים shloshim memorial for, or lunch for Rifka, and
we were mentioning that in addition to her always raising the moral
issues when it came to women's issues, she would also always raise
it when it came to animal issues, she would perk up anytime
there was some discussion relating to animals. So it is interesting this
issue about walking your dog and cleaning up after your dog on
שבת Shabbos because to what degree is it גרף של רעי garf
shel re'i if you are doing it because it is the law
of the city and you will get fined if you leave the
poop around, but it is not like it is in front of
you and it is disgusting to have, it is not the same
as in your room and it is smelling up your room. Of
course you could say, look, it is still just making the whole
environment disgusting for everybody who is going to walk on the street.
Okay, but it is a little different the context in which you
are cleaning up the poop there. Yes? In this case, is there
any relation to this and wanting to get rid of bugs on
שבת? Shabbos? Is that, where does capturing come in? Yeah, so that
is different. You are right that sometimes if you are afraid that
some animal or a bee is going to sting you or whatever,
there are cases in which they allowed either killing or capturing based
on concerns about צער tza'ar and again like the גמרא Gemara said
before if it was something that fundamentally was not trapped. But that
is different. I mean it is true, they are all like allowances,
but this is a particular מוקצה muktzah allowance because it is smelly
and disgusting and you have other types of allowances for other things.
This is a dead animal, it's a dead animal. Dead animal, yeah,
yeah, decaying and smelling up your perfume. Exactly. Exactly. Oh yeah, sorry,
I'm sorry, the juxtaposition, right, right, right, I'm sorry I wasn't clear
about that. That explains your question. Yeah, otherwise you would chase it
away. Right, right, no, it's dead, and it's therefore smelly. Exactly. Rotting,
decaying carcass. Okay, now we move to this next משנה mishnah which
is, seems to introduce some very important and interesting categories. Let's take
a look. Also seems to be an early משנה, mishnah, particularly based
on the last line, although maybe that's how it's constructed. But let's
take a look. כל שחייבין עליו משום שבות, kol shechayavin alav mishum
shevus, anything that you would transgress by, you would get to do
would be a transgression of שבות, shevus, which is understood as a
rabbinic enactment on שבת Shabbos to protect שבת, Shabbos, or we'll see
to create more of the nature of שבת, Shabbos, or to protect
from violation. משום רשות, mishum reshus, or if it's an issue that
maybe would have some type of a justification, which that's what רשות
reshus here means in this context, not just totally discretionary, but also
there would be some perhaps some justification to do it. או משום
מצוה, o mishum mitzvah, even something that there would be actually a
מצוה mitzvah to do, but nevertheless it comes up against a rabbinic
restriction. בשבת חייבין עליו ביום טוב. beShabbos chayavin alav beYom Tov. So
if these would be issues on שבת, Shabbos, you similarly transgress on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the basic point is two points. Number
one is there's not distinctions between, we just talked about making שבת
Shabbos parallel to יום טוב, Yom Tov, and we did find in
some cases maybe we're a little bit more מחמיר machmir here, a
little more מחמיר machmir there, but in this broad category called שבות,
shevus, it applies equally to שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov,
the same things apply in both. That's one point. And the second
point is that even when there's some reason to justify, רשות reshus
and מצוה mitzvah and whatever, it's not going to override. Again, quite
interesting in juxtaposition of the discussion we just had, which says that
it's not always שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov are the
same, right? That was the whole half of the עמוד amud we
just spent going through. And that there are things that sometimes do
justify certain overriding. This משנה mishnah saying the basic rule is they
are the same and things don't justify overriding them, whether רשות reshus
or מצוה. mitzvah. Now what are they? ואלו הן משום שבות. ve'elu
hen mishum shevus. These are the things that are straight out right,
a שבות shevus rabbinically forbidden that there would be no real justification.
These are the easy cases. לא עולין באילן, lo olin be'ilan, you
don't climb a tree, ולא רוכבין על גבי בהמה, velo rochvin al
gabei behemah, you don't ride an animal, ולא שטין על פני המים,
velo shatin al pnei hamayim, you don't go ahead and swim on
the water, or float on the water, you don't take a raft
on the water. ולא מטפחין, velo metapchin, and you don't clap, ולא
מספקין, velo mesapkin, another clap, רש״י Rashi says one is clapping with
hands, the other's clapping against your thigh, ולא מרקדין, velo merakdin, you
don't dance. ואלו הן משום רשות. ve'elu hen mishum reshus. So those
are the things that are שבות, shevus, that there's no real justification
to do and they're rabbinically forbidden. ואלו הן משום רשות. ve'elu hen
mishum reshus. Here are things that are also rabbinically forbidden but you
might have thought there's some justification and even so it doesn't matter.
לא דנין, lo danin, you can't be a בית דין, beis din,
even though you have בית דין, beis din, that's an important thing,
to sit in דין. din. ולא מקדשין, velo mekadeshin, you
can't get married, you can't do קידושין. kiddushin. ולא חולצין, velo choltzin,
you can't do חליצה, chalitza, ולא מיבמין, velo meyabmin, you can't do
יבום. yibum. Okay, now it's funny why these are called רשות, reshus,
since the קידושין, kiddushin, חליצה, chalitza, יבום, yibum, you'd think that they
would be called מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara will discuss
that.
But these are things which have some מצוה mitzvah element and even
so they can't be done. ואלו הן משום מצוה, ve'elu hen mishum
mitzvah, the following things are straight straight-out מצות mitzvos and nevertheless they
can't be done on שבת, Shabbos, לא מקדישין, lo makdishin, you can't
sanctify, ולא מעריכין, v'lo maarichin, also another way of saying ערך עלי,
erech alai, accepting an obligation to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, ולא
מחרימין, v'lo machrimin, also another way of sanctifying objects to the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, basically three different ways of taking בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash obligations or sanctifications, ולא מגביהין תרומות ומעשרות, v'lo magbihin trumos u'maasros,
and you don't separate תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, we've heard about that.
כל אלו ביום טוב אמרו, kol eilu b'Yom Tov amru, all of
these things were said by יום טוב, Yom Tov, קל וחומר בשבת,
kal v'chomer b'Shabbos, and how much more so by שבת. Shabbos. I
gotta tell you, there's a certain irony here. The משנה Mishnah starts
by saying
everything that's forbidden on שבת Shabbos is also forbidden on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, and here's the whole
list, and then they
say, these things
were initially taught that they
were forbidden on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and they also apply on
שבת. Shabbos. So what was the original context? שבת Shabbos or יום
טוב? Yom Tov? The language of שבות shvus also suggests שבת, Shabbos,
but in the end it says כל אלו ביום טוב אמרו, kol
eilu b'Yom Tov amru, and it is being taught in ביצה, Beitzah,
it's not being taught in שבת. Shabbos. Okay, and then it ends
אין בין יום טוב לשבת אלא אוכל נפש בלבד. ein bein Yom
Tov l'Shabbos ela ochel nefesh bilvad. So these דרבננ'ס d'rabanans are not
a difference. The difference is things that are directly involved in eating.
None of this is directly involved in eating. As you know, that's
the line from the משניות mishnayos in מגילה Megillah that have the
אין בין, ein bein, it's assumed to be a very early line.
So does that mean that the whole משנה Mishnah is early? Does
it mean that they are two different things that have been pasted
together? A very fascinating משנה, Mishnah, but one that does seem to
be early and gets to some interesting conceptual categories here about שבות
shvus and רשות. reshus. So again, it is worth noting that the
issue about רשות reshus and מצוה mitzvah is somewhat different. I said
even though there's a justification, it doesn't override. Normally we're talking about
you have a general principle, like, you know, I don't know, don't
move מוקצה, muktzah, and then you have a special case, גרף של
רעי, graf shel re'i, that's going to be an override. Here, the
basic דרבנן d'rabanan was initially framed in terms of this activity. There's
an activity of getting married. There's an activity of sitting in a
בית דין. Beis Din. There's an activity of, you know, sanctifying things.
And that activity, which itself is intrinsically a מצוה mitzvah or has
certain מצוה mitzvah elements to it, they directly said you're not allowed
to do that act. So again, it's not saying that there are
some types of external overrides, but here there are things that were
identified as activities, sometimes they're even מצוה mitzvah activities, that are forbidden.
Okay. Yes. Rabbi, wouldn't these last three be these examples of הקדשות
hekdeshos to the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? Okay, yeah, let's not unpack
that now. But just one quick- wouldn't that not be potentially relevant
to how you could have an appeal for? Yeah, it would potentially
be, although the appeal is more promise in the future, this is
actually effecting a status change immediately. Thanks. All right. I want to
get to the first section here because it's very important in terms
of how the בבלי Bavli conceptualizes this as opposed to other ways
of thinking about this. לא עולין באילן, lo olin b'ilan, you don't
climb a tree, גזרה שמא יתלוש, gezeirah shema yislosh, because you climb
a tree, you'll pull off a branch. ולא רוכבין על גבי בהמה,
v'lo rochvin al gabei beheimah, you don't ride an animal, גזרה שמא
יצא חוץ לתחום, gezeirah shema yeitzei chutz l'tchum, because you'll be riding
on an animal, you won't be paying close attention to how far
you've gone and you'll go outside of the תחום. tchum. So the
גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה תחומין דאורייתא? shma mina tchumin d'oraisa? Does
that mean to infer that תחומין tchumin are biblical? There's a question
whether תחומין tchumin are biblical or not. And if we're making a
גזרה, gezeirah, a protection, then presumably we're protecting a biblical violation. So
you don't want to be forced into that corner. אלא גזרה שמא
יחתוך זמורה. ela gezeirah shema yachotoch zmora. Okay, it's a different גזרה.
gezeirah. If you're riding an animal, you'll come to break off a
branch from a tree to use as a, you know, to- as
a stick to hit the animal. ולא שטין על פני המים, v'lo
shtin al pnei hamayim, you cannot like float on a- you know,
on a raft on the water, גזרה שמא יעשה חבית של שייטין,
gezeirah shema yaaseh chavis shel shayitin, because we're afraid that you'll make
a like- a, you know, what's it called? Like a tube, a,
what are those things called? A raft or, you know, תוספות Tosafos
even says it's like a small little steel barrel. What are those
called? Those inflatable tubes? Inflatable tubes. No, what do they call those
things that are made to- for floating? What? Air mattress? Air mattress.
Something like that. Anyway, you're afraid you'll make a flotation device. Okay.
And therefore that's the concern. ולא מטפחין ולא מספקין ולא מרקדין, v'lo
mtapchin v'lo msapkin v'lo mrakdin, you don't clap on your hands and
thighs and dance, גזרה שמא יתקן כלי שיר, gezeirah shema ytaken kli
shir, you start doing this, next thing you know you'll be fixing-
not making, but fixing musical instruments. Okay. And then it's going to
go on to the second categories of רשות reshus and מצוה. mitzvah.
But I want to just stop for a moment and say something.
The גמרא Gemara here did what the בבלי Bavli often does, which
is take certain דרבננ'ס d'rabanans and see them through the light of
גזרה. gezeirah. גזרה gezeirah you'll do this, גזרה gezeirah you'll do that,
גזרה gezeirah you'll do that, it's all to protect you from some
other violation. That is not necessarily the פשט pshat at all in
these things about שבות. shvus. If I tell you you don't ride
on an animal on שבת, Shabbos, you know the famous story with
אלישע בן אבויה Elisha ben Avuya and רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, right?
When it wants to sort of illustrate how אלישע Elisha was so
much, you know, rejecting the whole, you know, his- you know, his
tradition, it says he was riding on an animal on שבת Shabbos
and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was following him and he was teaching
him הלכה halacha and so on. So is the point, oh, I
got- because גזרה שמא יחתוך זמורה? gezeirah shema yachotoch zmora? You know,
that's not the image that comes in our mind. The sense is
that that type of activity, which is fundamentally improper on שבת, Shabbos,
call what's been called before עובדא דחול, uvda d'chol, right? But you
know, it's sort of like getting into your vehicles on שבת, Shabbos,
even if it's not going to lead to anything, that's- It doesn't
protect the sense of the קדושה kedusha and the focus on Shabbat;
it more evokes the larger world of business and so on. How
about the idea of clapping and dancing? If you look in the
תוספתא, Tosefta, the original context is you're out in the field and
you're clapping and jumping up and down to do what? To scare
away the birds. Okay, so that's what it is. We're talking about
things that technically are no, there is no actual מלאכה, melacha, but
you're involving yourself in business-type of activity. You know, and all these
types of things, you know, floating on the river, you go take
a raft trip down a river, you know, that's a major general
means of like transport, you know, and moving goods down the river.
So all of these things could be explained; שבות shvut does not
in its word suggest גזירה שמא, gezeira shema, a safeguard. שבות shvut
suggests the whole context of Shabbat. It's a way to preserve the
quality of Shabbat, it's central to the experience of Shabbat. It basically
is what we have been calling עובדא דחול. ovda d'chol. And the
irony is, is that when things are עובדא דחול, ovda d'chol, they
feel much more amorphous, not real הלכה. halacha. Yeah, it doesn't feel
right. But it could be some of the earliest תקנות takanot that
they made about Shabbat were these things called שבות, shvut, which were
about that experiential reality of Shabbat. And they specifically identified certain things
and made them forbidden. If you think about the whole list, right?
Sitting in a בית דין, beit din, right? Going ahead and sanctifying
things, purchasing things. Are these גזירות שמא gezeirot shema or are they
because this is activity, this is weekday activity? And that's what the
whole idea of שבות... shvut... climbing a tree. Why do people climb
trees? To pick fruit! Because they were workers! Right? So all of
these are very much work-like behavior and work-like activities. So many scholars
believe that in the משנה, Mishnah, in the תוספתא, Tosefta, probably even
in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, these remain at the level of שבות shvut
as things that are intrinsically problematic. The בבלי Bavli winds up reframing
them as a גזירה. gezeira. And part of reframing them as a
גזירה gezeira has an important implication להלכה. l'halacha. On the one hand,
you could say it devalues concerns of עובדא דחול, ovda d'chol, which
is there's probably some truth to that; if we understood these as
being about עובדא דחול, ovda d'chol, we'd give more weight to them.
The other issue is, is that if it's a גזירה, gezeira, there
might be circumstances where it doesn't apply. So for example, the idea
of clapping and dancing. Well, we clap and dance in שול, shul,
I mean some שולן shuln do, we do, not all שולן. shuln.
So תוספות Tosafot comes along and says yeah, because nowadays nobody really
knows how to fix a musical instrument like you know, in an
easy way, and since there's not the concern that we'll come to
fix musical instruments, the גזירה gezeira doesn't apply. You can only go
down that path if you think it's about a גזירה. gezeira. If
you think it's something that's an intrinsic problem, then there's not going
to be any of that possible contextualizing of it. Okay. Right. It's
only out in the field, it's not in the שול. shul. Right,
that could also be. What type of clapping are we talking about?
So that distinction could apply. But it is worth noting that the
בבלי Bavli has a tendency to make everything a גזירה. gezeira. Okay.
Let me give you one final example about this. Blowing a שופר
shofar on Shabbat, reading the מגילה Megillah on Shabbat, taking the לולב
lulav on Shabbat. Right? The בבלי Bavli frames it all as גזירה
gezeira you'll come to carry. It's not necessarily what that was about.
Certainly something like blowing a שופר, shofar, right, could more be like
making this noise, Shabbat is supposed to be quiet, it's a musical
instrument and so on. So it's definitely worth taking a step back
and realizing what it has done by framing the issues in the
משנה Mishnah this way. Okay.